Well, it's going to get really exciting now because we want to cover something called variables.
Now, before you think what in the world, all those things in life, we all need places to store things.
So I mean, if you've got shoes, I mean, maybe you're going to store those in a cupboard unless you've
got a lot of shoes.
Um, if you've got food, you know, milk and cheese and things like that, you're going to store that
in a refrigerator.
If you've got a car, you're going to store that in a garage.
All of these things need to be stored somewhere.
And those are handy containers.
And the same applies when it comes to programming.
We need to store things because sometimes you need to remember things.
So maybe you need to remember a high score in a game or what the counter is and something.
There are so many reasons you need to remember things, and those little containers that you store things
in that you want to remember are called variables.
So let's take a look at how you implement variables in inside of Python.
Okay.
So this is how we uh use variables.
So basically the syntax for creating a new variable is very simple.
So let's just say I want to store my name.
I create a variable called name by just typing name.
We then put a equals which is known as an assignment operator.
And we equal it to whatever we would like name to store.
So again I'm going to store Sarah.
So all this is doing is it's just taking the word Sarah.
And it's now storing it inside the cupboard or a container.
Container name.
So in this case the variable is very important that you give your variables a a name that is meaningful.
So for example we could have actually called this x.
But later on when you're starting to work with your variables you're going to say what was x.
Ah I can't remember.
So always give your variables a useful name.
So because this particular variable is storing name we've done.
In fact we might even want to be more specific and call it first name.
So simply it's taking Sarah's name.
Now notice her name is in inverted commas.
It's very important.
We'll explain that in a moment and it's assigning it into the variable.
Then there are also a couple of names that you can't use as variables.
So firstly one thing you cannot do or a name you cannot make a variable is you can't make a variable
start with a capital letter.
This just isn't syntactically correct.
Uh, programmers never, ever start their line of code with a capital letter for almost anything.
And all those years when your English language teachers told you to do that.
And there it goes out the window.
That's what we like about programming.
It messes with the rules.
Okay, the next thing you can't do is start with a number or any symbol.
As soon as I do that, you'll see that this has actually changed color because it no longer understands
what you are doing.
So you can't start with a number.
You can't start with a symbol.
Basically, you keep it simple.
Tap in your variable name, something that makes sense, and then just assign it to what you want.
Now you could, if you wanted, um, call it first name number one.
It's okay to put a number at the end of it.
Uh, because maybe you are storing first name one, first name two or something.
So that's okay.
But generally keep it simple, keep it in lowercase and keep it something that makes sense okay.
So you'll see that if I print if I run this program, it's not going to do anything.
And that's because I haven't actually printed anything.
So now let's print our variable.
Okay.
So what we basically want to do is we want to print the name Sarah, but we want to print it using the
variables name which is first name.
So to do that now all you have to do is type the variables name.
So you'll notice here I haven't put it in inverted commas or anything.
If it's a variable you just type it as it is nothing around it.
And now when we run it you'll see it's now printed.
So because it's variable that's all it's really done is it's printing what's stored inside of here.
And seriously it's very important that that is not in inverted commas.
What do you think would happen if we put it inverted commas?
Think about it.
What would happen if we put inverted commas around this.
So put two inverted commas and run it.
It's actually printing the word.
First name.
Just like it printed the word Sarah.
So it now thinks it's just what's called a string and it's just printing that.
So with a variable, you don't put your variable in inverted commas because you're actually interested
in what's stored inside of it.
It's a container.
So we can remove those.
And we will be able to print the name that is stored in there.
Now what's also nice with variables and this is where we'll see it becomes powerful is we can just change
what goes into the variable.
So we can, uh, put my name here now.
And so without changing this piece of code, we'll notice at the bottom it changes to print my name.
So it's changing because it's merely printing what's stored inside the variable.
So that is how variables work.
Really simple.
And once again you can really put whatever you want inside of these inverted commas.
But whatever's inside of the inverted commas now becomes first name.
So if I wanted to make changes into maybe a greeting.
Now it's going to print.
Craig, how are you?
So you can make this as long as you want, but obviously you want to make something that makes sense.
Now, that's no longer really makes sense because we've called it first name and we've said, Craig,
how are you?
So you might want to change this to being called greeting and rather print greeting.
Um, so there's a lot more we're going to do with variables.
We use them in every, almost every single thing.
Uh, they probably one of the most important parts of programming.
Now, notice I have changed it to greeting.
What do you think is going to happen now?
I'm going to say greeting Craig, how are you?
And then we're going to say print first name.
Okay.
You'll see down here Python is not happy.
It's basically telling you in the midst of all of this, it's saying on line three.
On line three you'll see over here something bad is happening.
It says, you've got this thing where it says print first name, but I don't know what it is.
First name is not defined.
Behind.
Okay, so what it's really saying is there is no variable called firstname.
So you go, ah, see, I made a mistake because I changed the name of my variable.
My variable is actually greeting.
So if I run it now there we go.
Another common mistake people do make is if you put this print statement before the greeting statement,
what do you think is going to happen again?
It says it's not defined.
So this might be confusing because you'll say you have defined it down here.
But the way Python works is it reads what you've written from top to bottom.
So if you've printed greeting but haven't defined greeting before you printed it, it doesn't know what
you're talking about because it's read line one print greeting.
And that's all it's read.
It hasn't seen you define the variable greeting on line three.
Okay.
So it is very important that you define your variables up front and load them with the content before
you try and work with them.
So that's basically your intro to variables.
So have some fun.
Create a little variable as many as you like, and use the print command or the print statement.
And you can print out what's in them.
Go have some fun.